מזל טוב. Mazel Tov. Today's דף daf is דף כ"ח. Daf Kaf-Chet.
We're a little ahead, so maybe we can even get a full
דף daf ahead. We start on
כ"ח עמוד ב' Kaf-Chet Amud Bet and we start from where it
says והא
דתני רב יוסף. ve-ha detani Rav Yosef. We'll pick up from there,
four lines from the top. So the discussion had been what things
cause טומאת נגעים tumat nega'im and excuse me, not טומאת נגעים, tumat
nega'im, טומאת אוהלים. tumat ohalim. We learned out from the משכן mishkan
that on certain types of fabrics, the types used in the משכן,
mishkan, that if they are actually made into a tent, can then
even though normally things attached to the ground will not be טמא,
tamei, they will become טמא tamei if there's a dead body in
it, not just things under the tent, but the tent itself. And
the question was what about leather from non-kosher animals? And there was
a discussion whether the תחש tachash was kosher and not kosher, can
we learn it out from נגעים, nega'im, from other places? Anyway, so
we sort of have resolved it sounds like leather from non-kosher animals
is included. And now the question is what is the relevance of
the teaching of רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. So let's take a look
at what we looked at yesterday. והא דתני רב יוסף, ve-ha detani
Rav Yosef, that which רב יוסף Rav Yosef taught, לא הוכשרו למלאכת
שמים אלא עור בהמה טהורה בלבד, lo huchshru limlechet shamayim ela or
behema tehora bilvad, that the only thing used for heavenly purposes was
the leather of kosher animals. If it's not to tell us a
teaching about the משכן mishkan for the purposes of this law of
the טומאה tumah of tents, because there even non-kosher leathers, leathers of
non-kosher animals are included, למאי הלכתא, le-mai hilchata, what was the purpose
of teaching it, whether it was or wasn't true for the משכן,
mishkan, if it has no practical relevance why did he teach it?
So למאי הלכתא? le-mai hilchata? So the גמרא Gemara says, תפילין, tefillin,
to tell me about תפילין, tefillin, that you cannot use leather from
non-kosher animals for תפילין. tefillin. So the גמרא Gemara says תפילין? tefillin?
בהדיא כתיב, behedya ketiv, in תפילין tefillin you don't need him to
tell it to me, we know it from a פסוק, pasuk, למען
תהיה תורת ה' בפיך, lema'an tihye torat Hashem beficha, so the תורה
Torah of God should be in your mouth. That's from one of
the פסוקים pesukim from the four פרשיות parshiyot of תפילין. tefillin. And
we say מן המותר בפיך, min hamutar beficha, you can only make
תפילין tefillin from something that you can put in your mouth, from
an animal that's a kosher animal, so you wouldn't have needed him
to tell me that.
He says for תורה Torah and other ספרי תורה. sifrei torah.
All right, this is the way they make the דרשה. drasha. אלא
לאורן, ela le-oran, fine, not to tell me that the קלף, klaf,
which is where you have the תורת ה', torat Hashem, which is
written on the קלף, klaf, that not only tell me that the
קלף klaf has to be kosher—and Mike's correct, it's not necessarily limited
to תפילין, tefillin, any type of a scroll that has קדושה, kedusha,
whether it's מזוזה, mezuzah, whether it's תפילין, tefillin, whether it's ספר תורה,
sefer torah, that's the תורת ה', torat Hashem, that's the קלף—רב יוסף
is teaching me that even the leather used for the boxes, that
has to be from a kosher animal. One minute, והאמר אביי, ve-ha
amar Abaye, but one minute, you don't need a special teaching of
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef you can learn it out from what אביי
Abaye says, because אביי Abaye says שי"ן של תפילין הלכה למשה מסיני,
shin shel tefillin halacha le-moshe mi-sinai, that the שי"ן shin on the
של ראש shel rosh is a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha le-moshe mi-sinai.
So if the שי"ן shin is one of the letters of God's
name and it represents God's name in itself, or רש"י Rashi says
you combine the שי"ן shin on the ראש rosh with the דל"ת
dalet at the back of the head with the יו"ד yud on
the של יד shel yad and you get God's name, although תוספות
tosafot questions whether you consider the letters made out of the רצועות
retzuot as considered letters as written letters, but regardless at least the
שי"ן shin is a letter of God's name and that's on the
leather of the תפילין, tefillin, so that also is in the פסוק
pasuk of תורת ה' בפיך. torat Hashem beficha. So we already know
it from there, you don't need רב יוסף's Rav Yosef, teaching. So
the גמרא Gemara says אלא לכרכן בשערן ולתפרן בגידן, ela le-charchan be-se'aran
u-letafren be-gidan,
for another הלכה, halacha, that the קלפים klafim that you put inside
the boxes of תפילין, tefillin, you wrap a little string around it
to keep those in like scroll-like shape. And there even is a
הלכה halacha about that when you put those little scrolls in the
תפילין, tefillin, you scroll it up and then you wrap a little
string around it and tighten it so it stays in that shape.
Yes, so it stays in that shape. Now that string cannot just
be any string you want, that has to be a string made
out of hair from a kosher animal.
Is this for של ראש shel rosh or של יד?
shel yad?
I think it's for both, certainly for the של ראש. shel rosh.
So that's that, ולתפרן בגידן. u-letafren be-gidan. Now when you have a,
now
this
I don't know normally you have this by תפילין, tefillin, but anyway,
but when you normally have, but in a ספר תורה sefer torah
certainly you have different קלפים klafim and you tie all
the, not tie, sew the קלפים klafim together.
You're talking about the בית? bayit?
Maybe you're right, let me see what רש"י Rashi says. גדי בר
בשורא Gidi bar Bishora says,
רש"י Rashi seems to be saying that it's talking
about the פרשיות parshiyot themselves.
Maybe you're right though, at least that would work. We're on כ"ח
עמוד ב', Kaf-Chet Amud Bet, we're about 20 lines down. Okay, so
why? What do your commentary say there? Do they say what's somewhere
around? Yeah.
Yeah,
it's customary to tie the תורה Torah portion itself and then roll
it in a piece of parchment. parchment and tie it again. It's
also customary to use the hair of a calf. If one does
not have calf's hair, one may tie it with the hair of
a cow or an ox.
So it's talking about.
No, that's about the לכורכן בשערן. lichorchan b'saaran. How about לתופרן בגידן?
letophran b'gidan? Doesn't say anything.
The boxes phylacteries are sewn shut using sinews of a kosher...
oh, so it's like דוסא. Dosa. Or non-domesticate.
Okay, okay, so it's like דוסא Dosa said. So there because by
yeah by תפילין tefillin you have the you have each פרשה parsha
or by the של יד shel yad all four פרשיות parshiot on
a single קלף. klaf But when you do deal with the ספר
תורה Sefer Torah Joe, I don't know there's
a problem here, but when
you deal with a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, you do have multiple
parchments and you do sew them together and you use a string
essentially a type of a thread that is made from the sinews
of the intestines of kosher animals. That's the גידן. gidan. So that
it says has to be only from kosher animals. Again by תפילין
tefillin you don't have that you have single parchments so I appreciate
it wasn't clear from רש״י Rashi but I appreciate the point that
דב Dov made which is that we're talking about sewing the boxes
shut. That's it, let's just finish this. So therefore it says that's
what you need the teaching of רב יוסף Rav Yosef to say
that you can only use kosher animals to sew to use for
the hair of the string to tie the parchments in the rolls
to keep them in their rolls or the sinews to sew up
the boxes can only be from kosher animals. So the גמרא Gemara
says ואמר רב יצחק רצועות שחורות הלכה למשה מסיני. v'amar Rav Yitzchak
ritsuot shchorot halacha l'moshe misinai. So the גמרא Gemara says,
I'm sorry I skipped a line. So the גמרא Gemara says הנמי
הלכה למשה מסיני הוא. hanamie halacha l'moshe misinai hu.
But so what? That's also הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai and
we don't get that from רב יוסף. Rav Yosef דתניא תפילין מרובעות
הלכה למשה מסיני. d'tanya tefillin m'rubbaot halacha l'moshe misinai.
The fact that they have to be square is הלכה למשה מסיני.
halacha l'moshe misinai. נכרכות בשערן ונתפרות בגידן nichrachot b'saaran v'nitparot b'gidan
that you wrap the parchments with the hair of the kosher animals
and that you sew up the boxes with the sinews that also
is included in הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'moshe misinai. So again if
it's הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai presumably the הלכה למשה מסיני
halacha l'moshe misinai includes it says בשערן, b'saaran, בגידן b'gidan
that it includes that it comes from the same kosher animals. So
that's not what רב יוסף Rav Yosef. is teaching. אלא לרצועות. ela
l'ritsuot. All right, what he's teaching is that the straps, those have
to be from kosher animals. The גמרא Gemara says ואמר רב יצחק
רצועות שחורות הלכה למשה מסיני. v'amar Rav Yitzchak ritsuot shchorot halacha l'moshe
misinai. But
one minute that's also part of the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe
misinai that the straps have to be black and presumably if the
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai is telling you the color of
the strap, presumably it's also telling you what animal, what leather the
straps come from. So the גמרא Gemara says no maybe here's exactly
where we need רב יוסף. Rav Yosef מדי גמירי שחורות טהורות מי
גמירי. midei gmirie shchorot tahorot mi gmirie. It's true we know black,
but we don't know that they had to be from kosher animals.
So רב יוסף Rav Yosef. is telling me you can only use
kosher leather for מלאכת שמים. melechet shamayim.
So what things do you use leather for? I mean you make
קלף claf. out of the hide but that we have another פסוק
pasuk and the only other thing you'll use leather for is for
תפילין. tefillin. So therefore we found one area תפילין tefillin which we
didn't already know what material the straps have to be and that's
what רב יוסף Rav Yosef says that you can only use kosher
leather. Let's finish now the point though which is we'll get to
the question in a minute let's finish the point about where you
get the about what whether the תחש tachash was a kosher or
non-kosher animal. Because we have learned for practical halachic purposes whether the
משכן Mishkan was made of only kosher skins or not that even
a skin of a non-kosher animal
has this טומאת אוהלים, tumat ohalim, the טומאה tuma of tents. Even
though we learn it from משכן, Mishkan, we learn it elsewhere that
that includes even skin of non-kosher animals. So therefore we don't know
whether the skin of this תחש tachash was kosher wasn't kosher doesn't
matter להלכה. l'halacha. But what's the story with this תחש? tachash? So
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי הוי עלה
דתחש? mai havi alei d'tachash? So what's the conclusion about this תחש
tachash היה בימי משה haya b'yemei Moshe that was in the time
of משה? Moshe?
אמר רבי אילא אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש amar Rabbi Ela amar
Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish excuse me
אומר היה רבי מאיר omer haya Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
used to say I mean שמעון בן לקיש Shimon ben Lakish excuse
me אומר היה רבי מאיר omer haya Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir used to say תחש היה בימי משה בריה בפני עצמה היה.
tachash haya b'yemei Moshe biria bifnei atzma haya. תחש tachash in the
time of משה Moshe was its own creature, meaning it was like
a unique creature was not a normal creature. ולא הכריעו בו חכמים
אם מין חיה אם מין בהמה הוא. v'lo hichriu bo chachamim im
min chaya im min behema hu. And the rabbis did not decide
whether it was in the חיה chaya or the בהמה behema category,
domesticated or non-domesticated.
There's another famous animal like that the כוי koy which the גמרא
Gemara has the question is it a חיה chaya or בהמה behema
and has relevant הלכות. halachot. Can you eat the חלב? chelev? Do
you have to cover the blood? Okay so that might be בריה
בפני עצמה biria bifnei atzma might not in itself mean there's none
other like it, might not be like it was a once in
a lifetime creature, might just mean it falls between two categories. But
we will continue to read that it does sound that it's almost
a mystical creature. Okay so the first point is it's not clear
whether it was a חיה chaya or בהמה. behema. וקרן אחת היתה
לו במצחו, v'keren achat hayta lo b'mitzcho, it had one horn in
its on its forehead. ולפי שעה נזדמן לו למשה, u'lfi sha'a nizdamen
lo l'Moshe, and just for the purposes of that time was it
did it appear or it sort of chance. before Moshe, ועשה ממנו
משכן, veasah mimenu mishkan, and he made from it a משכן, mishkan,
ונגנז, venignaz, and then it was hidden for for all future time.
So that makes it sound like בריה בפני עצמה biryah bifnei atzmah
is not just saying it's somewhere between חיה chayah and בהמה, beheimah,
but that it was a once-in-a-lifetime or once-in-a, you know, once in
a lifetime of the universe type of a creature. Maybe it's around,
but it only appeared once in the time of Moshe. Now the
fact that it says that it seems like it only appeared once
and it has a horn in the middle of a head makes
you think it's a mythical creature, that it's a unicorn. So maybe,
maybe that's what חז"ל Chazal thought,
but others do try to identify it with some type of a,
you know, animal that is more, that does really exist. So,
so we have now two features. Yesterday we mentioned it has multicolored
skin and today we have a horn in the center of its
head. Now no animal actually has a real like, you know, unicorn
type of horn, but there have been two attempts to, like what?
Rhino. Rhino, is that a, I think it's like, I think it's
more like a tooth or something. Narwhal? Yeah, so anyway, rhino might
have fit, but the problem is is that a rhino doesn't have
multicolored skin. So the two that they have suggested is narwhal, which
is this aquatic animal, which is, which apparently has spotted skin. It's
not kosher, well that's a possibility here. It's also not technically a
horn, but okay, I think it's some type of a tooth or
something. And the other possibility which is what Felix says,
the one who did the book on the flora and fauna
of the Torah and of the משנה, Mishnah, very important, before there
was Slifkin there, Felix is the one who was the real academic
that did all the work, and he basically said that, suggested that
it's a giraffe because a giraffe does have colors, you know, spots,
and it has like a little hump there in the center of
its head. So it's not normally what we would think of as
like a horn, but at least it's a little bit of a
raised bump. Right, it's not נגנז. nignaz. Maybe it was נגנז nignaz
to be around in the Sinai desert. Okay, and that would be
kosher. So this מחלוקת machlokes is the מחלוקת machlokes about whether it
was a kosher or non-kosher animal. So let's take a look, let's
just finish up to the משנה. mishna. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: ודיקאמר קרן אחת היתה לו במצחו, udeikaamar keren achat haytah
lo bemitzo, now this is going to answer whether it was kosher
or not. Since it said a horn in its forehead, שמע מינה
טהור היה, shema mina tahor hayah, you know it was kosher. How
do you know that? Because we have another, we have another animal
identified that had a horn in one horn in its head, which
was that? דאמר רבי יהודה שור שהקריב אדם הראשון קרן אחת היתה
לו במצחו. deamar Rabi Yehudah shor shehikriv Adam HaRishon keren achat haytah
lo bemitzo. The original ox that the first human being offered up
to God had a horn in the middle in its head, in
its forehead. שנאמר: sheneemar: ותיטב לה' משור פר מקרין מפריס. vetitav laShem
mishor par makrin mafris. So, it would be more pleasing to God
than the ox of a cow,
מקרין makrin מפריס. mafris. So, horn, the word here is קרן keren
from horn and מפריס mafris like פרסה parsah split hoofs. So the
גמרא Gemara suppose from there learns that it had a single horn.
The גמרא Gemara says: מקרין תרתי משמע. makrin tarti mashma. מקרין makrin
sounds like it's multiple, two horns. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
says, מקרן כתיב. mikeren ksiv. It's written without the יוד. yud. So
it has a single horn. מקרן mikeren and מפריס mafris it has
split hoofs and we learn, we have a tradition that that's talking
about the animal that אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon brought. So presumably that's
the animal, that's the תחש. tachash. What other animal has a single
horn? And here you have that it has, was a kosher animal.
When did אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon bring it?
You
obviously are not reading your בראשית Bereishis carefully enough. According to a
מדרש. midrash. It's not in the תורה. Torah. Right,
right, right. So the גמרא Gemara says: וליפשוט מיניה דמין בהמה הוא.
velifshot minei demin beheimah hu. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's
really the animal, we should also determine that it's a בהמה beheimah
because it called it a type of an ox. So the גמרא
Gemara says no: כיון דאיכא קרש דמין חיה הוא ולית ליה אלא
חדא קרן איכא למימר מין חיה הוא. keivan deika keresh demin chayah
hu veleit leih ela chada keren ika lemeimar min chayah hu. No,
because there is, there is also the קרש keresh which is a
type of a חיה chayah and that only has one horn. Okay,
I don't know how does it translate קרש keresh there? It doesn't.
It doesn't.
Okay, but a קרש keresh is a single-horned deer. See רש"י Rashi
there.
All right, anyway, so therefore it might be, it might be a
חיה. chayah. So just because you have identified one animal that was
a בהמה beheimah that had a single horn, there's another animal that's
a קרש keresh that has a single horn, so we don't know
if it was a חיה chayah or בהמה. beheimah. And presumably also
we don't still don't know if it's טהור tahor or לא טהור
lo tahor because maybe if there's more than one animal that has
a single horn, this also could have been a non-kosher animal that
had a single horn, so in the end we still don't know
what the story is with the תחש. tachash. You had a question?
Yes, so back to where it talks about
המותר בפיך. hamutar bepicha. Yes, that would seem to imply that it's
not only a kosher animal but it has to be properly שחוט.
shechted. I was going to ask the same question.
Not necessarily, that's, you know, that's talking about the, the species of
it, not that literally you eat, you don't eat the leather anyway.
And not only that, leather is not, you know, not kosher. The
kosher aspect is the meat. Meat. So you could actually, you know,
you can use leather of
non-kosher... That is
we're not talking about that. I mean, whatever. So anyway, okay, let's
take a look now at the next משנה. Mishnah. פתילת הבגד שקיפלה
ולא הבהבה. P'tilat habeged shekipela velo hivveva. Now, you have a little
swatch of a clothing that you have folded, but you have not
yet singed. So you understand, you took like a little piece of
clothing, you twisted it up to use as a wick, but you
haven't singed it. רבי אליעזר אומר טמאה ואין מדליקין בה. Rabbi Eliezer
omer tamea ve'ein madlikin bah. So it is טמאה, tamea, and a
separate הלכה, halacha, we'll see in a minute if they're linked, you
can't use it as a wick. רבי עקיבא אומר טהורה היא ומדליקין
בה. Rabbi Akiva omer tahora hi umadlikin bah. It is טהורה tahora
for טומאה tumah purposes. It doesn't count yet as clothing. We learned
yesterday that even a little piece if it's made certainly of cloth
or linen, three fingers by three fingers. Somehow because this you have
twisted up as a wick, it is טהורה, tahora, cannot become טמאה,
tamea, and you can use it as a wick. What טומאה tumah
has to do with using it as a wick seems unrelated. The
גמרא Gemara will have an approach, two approaches, whether these are linked
or not. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. בשלמא לענין
טומאה בהא פליגי. Bishlama le'inyan tumah be'ha peligi. We understand what it
comes to purposes of טומאה, tumah, we can understand this is the
debate. רבי אליעזר סבר קיפלה לא מועיל ובמילתא קמייתא קיימא. Rabbi Eliezer
savar kipela lo mo'il uvemilsa kammaita kaiya. Rabbi Eliezer holds that the
twisting does not help. So the question is when does this still
consider to be a piece of clothing and when is it a
wick? A wick isn't טמא. tame. If you have a wick even
you make it out of wool or linen, whatever, it's not טמא.
tame. טמא tame is a בגד. beged. True, a swath three by
three is טמא, tame, but that's because it's seen as a piece
of a בגד beged and can be used also as a type
of a, what's it called?
A patch. It's a type of a patch. So that's true, but
as soon as it stops being a piece of clothing and becomes
a wick, then it's not טמא. tame. So has it become a
wick when you twisted it? But it's not permanent. You could always
undo the twisting. Does it change its identity yet? So Rabbi Eliezer
says that the twisting does not help. ובמילתא קמייתא קיימא, uvemilsa kammaita
kaiya, it's still a swatch of clothing and you could untwist it
and therefore it could still become טמא. tame. רבי עקיבא סבר קיפלה
מועיל ובטולי בטיל. Rabbi Akiva savar kipela mo'il uvatulei batil. No, it's
changed its identity. Even if you haven't singed it, ובטולי בטיל, uvatulei
batil, it loses its status as clothing and now is a wick.
אלא לענין הדלקה במאי פליגי? Ella le'inyan hadlaka be'mai peligi? What are
they debating about using it for a wick for שבת? Shabbat? Now,
it could be simply a practical question. Does it draw the oil
well? But it seems like the גמרא Gemara would like to also
think that maybe these debates are linked rather than they just randomly
are two separate debates. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי יהושע וכן אמר רב אדא בר אבהא.
Amar Rabbi Eleazar amar Rabbi Yehoshua vechen amar Rav Adda bar Abba.
ג' על ג' מצומצמות עסקינן. Gimel al gimel metzumtzamot askinan. We're talking
about a swatch of clothing that is exactly three fingers by three
fingers. So if it gets any smaller, it stops being considered a
piece of clothing. וביום טוב שחל להיות ערב שבת עסקינן. Uveyom Tov
shechal lihyot erev Shabbat askinan. So already two assumptions we have to
read into the משנה. Mishnah. Number one, it's exactly three by three,
and number two, when you want to use it, you're using it
on not just a normal ערב שבת, erev Shabbat, you're lighting it,
but you're lighting it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. And now what's
the debate? דכולי עלמא אית להו דרבי יהודה. Dechulei alma is lehu
deRabbi Yehuda. Everybody agrees with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that we're going
to say in a minute. דאמר מסיקין בכלים ואין מסיקין בשברי כלים.
De'amar masikin bekelim ve'ein masikin beshivrei kelim. So there's a major debate
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon about יום
טוב Yom Tov where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has a much broader
category of מוקצה muktzah on יום טוב, Yom Tov, I should have
said about מוקצה, muktzah, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon has a much
smaller category of מוקצה. muktzah. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has a
larger category. So therefore for him you have a vessel that you
started on שבת Shabbat or יום טוב Yom Tov with and on
שבת Shabbat or יום טוב Yom Tov it broke. Are the shards
of that vessel, שיברי כלים, shivrei kelim, considered מוקצה muktzah or not?
When שבת Shabbat started, they were not מוקצה. muktzah. Now they're in
a different state and in a non-usable state. But maybe since it
was okay when שבת Shabbat entered, they remain non-מוקצה muktzah now. That's
the הלכה halacha of שיברי כלים. shivrei kelim. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says שיברי כלים shivrei kelim are נולד, nolad, they're born, they're a
new thing, they're מוקצה. muktzah. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says they're not.
So according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that they are a מוקצה
muktzah problem, that you broke a vessel on שבת, Shabbat, on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, or let's say יום טוב, Yom Tov, you can't
use it for your firewood. Because firewood is fine. Firewood started off
as wood when יום טוב Yom Tov began. This started off as
a vessel. If it had broken ערב יום טוב, erev Yom Tov,
then you could use the shards. Then you had before יום טוב
Yom Tov you had designated it for fuel and you could use
it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. But here it actually changed its
status when יום טוב Yom Tov began it was a vessel. On
יום טוב Yom Tov it became shards. You could not now
use this as firewood. This is something new. It's מוקצה muktzah and
you can't use it as firewood on יום טוב. Yom Tov. That's
what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. מסיקין בכלים, Masikin bekelim, you can
take your vessel and throw it in the fire, ואין מסיקין בשברי
כלים, ve'ein masikin beshivrei kelim, but you cannot use broken things, pieces
of a broken vessel that broke on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
And this cloth was broken.
דכולי עלמא אית להו דעולא. Dechulei alma is lehu deUlla. Everybody also
agrees to עולא. Ulla. דאמר עולא המדליק צריך שידליק ברוב היוצא. De'amar
Ulla hamadlik tzarich sheyidlik berov hayotze. When you are lighting the wick
on שבת, Shabbat, on ערב שבת, erev Shabbat, you have to make
sure you've lit most of the wick that's exposed. That's just to
keep
the
fire
burning. so you wait till most of the exposed wick is burning.
And therefore what? רבי אליעזר סבר קיפל אינה מועיל. Rabbi Eliezer savar
kipel einah mo'il. Remember רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said, and now here's
how we're going to tie the debates together. The reason it can
be it can become טמא tamei is because even after you twist
it, it's still considered a garment. It's not yet considered a wick.
That's why it can become טמא. tamei. So it's a piece of
garment. So now what's going to happen? It's a כלי. kli. וכיון
דאדליק בה פורתא, Vekivan de'adlik ba purta, so now on יום טוב
Yom Tov which is ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, you start lighting it.
And as soon as you lit a little bit and a little
burnt, so it's less than three by three. It's less than three
by three, it stops being a vessel because it started off as
a swath of clothing, less than three by three doesn't count as
a swath. It's a שבר כלי, shever kli, it's like a broken
vessel. הוי ליה שבר כלי. Havei le shever kli. Now, but you
can't just light it and move away, you have to keep on
fiddling with it till most of it gets lit. And therefore you
are handling a broken vessel on יום טוב. Yom Tov. וכי קמדליק
בשבר כלי קמדליק, Vechi kamadlik beshever kli kamadlik, so then you are
handling a broken vessel. Do you understand how this works? If it
had,
well let's say conversely to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא סבר
קיפל מועיל, Rabbi Akiva savar kipel mo'il, as soon as you twisted
it by ערב יום טוב Erev Yom Tov let's say, you made
it into a wick. It stopped being a swath. So if it's
like a wick, it stops, it's not a שבר כלי, shever kli,
it's like it started יום טוב Yom Tov as a שבר כלי,
shever kli, it started like a piece of firewood, right? Firewood, if
you start יום טוב Yom Tov with firewood, you can use it
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, it didn't change its status on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. ואין תורת כלי עליו, Ve'ein toras kli alav,
it doesn't start as a vessel on יום טוב. Yom Tov. It
starts as a wick. וכי קמדליק בעץ בעלמא קמדליק, Vechi kamadlik be'etz
b'alma kamadlik, and when you're lighting it, you're lighting a stick. Now,
a normal stick you find in the middle of the forest is
מוקצה. muktzah. But sticks that you set aside from before יום טוב
Yom Tov to use as firewood, right, those aren't מוקצה. muktzah. And
therefore this is not a problem about using it on יום טוב
Yom Tov because by the time יום טוב Yom Tov began, it
was already a wick. So that's how we made the debate, the
debates connected. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says this is not a wick,
it's a piece of cloth. It can become, it's טמא. tamei. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's a wick and it cannot become טמא.
tamei. And therefore can you use it to light for your שבת
Shabbos candles? Well, שבת Shabbos ערב יום טוב, Erev Yom Tov, so
according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you're turning it from cloth into
a broken cloth into non-cloth. That makes it מוקצה, muktzah, you have
to stop using it. And since you're supposed to be fiddling with
the light for a few till you get it going good, you'll
be handling מוקצה. muktzah. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it started יום
טוב Yom Tov as a wick, it didn't change its status, it's
not מוקצה. muktzah. And that's how we make the debate connected. Okay,
but that assumes a couple of assumptions both about that it's יום
טוב Yom Tov and about the position of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רב יוסף היינו דתנינא,
Amar Rav Yosef haynu detanina, ah that makes sense because we have
a ברייתא Baraita that says ג' על ג' מצומצמות, gimel al gimel
metzumtzamot, exactly three by three, presumably clarifying this debate. ולא ידענא למאי
הלכתא, V'lo yadanah l'mai hilchasa, I didn't know what was the point
of saying that. I mean, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say this
piece of cloth is טמא tamei even bigger than three by three,
why did it say exactly three by three? Now, מדאמרת השתא בר
אהבה mid'amarta Hashta bar Ahava ליה אליבא דרבי יהודה, lei aliba d'Rabbi
Yehuda, now that we've explained this whole thing according to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and it was יום טוב Yom Tov ערב שבת Erev
Shabbos and the problem was about a broken vessel, שמע מינה דרבי
יהודה סבירא ליה, shema mina d'Rabbi Yehuda svira le, okay so I'm
sorry, שמע מינה דרבי יהודה סבירא ליה. shema mina d'Rabbi Yehuda svira
le. So now we hear that he holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda and
and therefore, wait,
I'm sorry, I put the period in the wrong place. היינו דתנינא
ג' על ג' מצומצמות ולא ידענא למאי הלכתא, Haynu detanina gimel al
gimel metzumtzamot v'lo yadanah l'mai hilchasa, period. Meaning, now I get this
ברייתא Baraita that said exactly three by three. Originally, I didn't know
why we were saying exactly three by three, right? For רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer to say the cloth is טמא, tamei, certainly he would
say a bigger cloth is טמא. tamei. Now I get why we
said exactly three by three to explain the debate of using it
for שבת Shabbos candles because if it's exactly three by three and
it happens to be יום טוב Yom Tov before שבת Shabbos and
and and and you start burning it and now it's less than
three by three then you can't use it. So that's why we
said it
was three by three and you start burning it it would still
be bigger than three by three.
Right, so for רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer it wouldn't have a problem.
Exactly, but because it's exactly three by three then you know by
necessity that as soon as it starts burning for one second, now
it's going to be a שבר כלי. shever kli. Exactly, so now
I get why we explained the משנה Mishnah that way.
And he ripped on יום טוב Yom Tov to be that size.
No, it was before יום טוב Yom Tov and it wouldn't be.
No, no,
you missed the point.
Before יום טוב Yom Tov it was three by three, it was
a piece of clothing. Then on יום טוב, Yom Tov, that was
before יום טוב, Yom Tov, on יום טוב Yom Tov you started
lighting it, the burning of it made it less than three by
three. So it started יום טוב Yom Tov as a piece of
clothing, anything that's three by three because it can become טמא, tamei,
it's all connected. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's three by three,
even though you twisted it, it's clothing, not a wick, therefore can
become טמא tamei and therefore when יום טוב Yom Tov started it
was a piece of clothing. You started burning it, you got a
little less than three by three.
But this twisted bit doesn't make a difference? It doesn't make this
thing as a wick?
No, that's
exactly רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi Eliezer's point. That's exactly the debate. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says it's still clothing, that's why it can become טמא.
tamei. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, it's already a wick.
Yes.
You start out with four by four, you twist
it.
Yes, but then you are not handling it. מוקצה muktzeh is only
a problem of handling. If it's burning, if you throw a vessel
in the fire, you're allowed to. At that stage it's not מוקצה.
muktzeh. Now it keeps on burning, that's not your problem, you're not
handling. Now you say, are you allowed to get הנאה hana'ah from
מוקצה, muktzeh, whatever, okay, so that's more of a discussion in ביצה.
Beitzah. But for now the focus is that as long as you're
not handling it, and that's why we said if it's exactly three
by three and you have to handle the wick for a few
seconds, then at those few seconds it'll be some less than three
by three and be a שבר כלי. shever kli.
And do you need—is this a problem just on יום טוב? Yom
Tov? Not—meaning יום טוב Yom Tov is ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos.
Yeah, what's the problem? It's a—so you handled a שבר כלי shever
kli on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. It's a מוקצה muktzeh problem.
No, but about טומאה tumah and stuff.
No, no, there are separate debates, they are connected. The טומאה tumah
issue is a general issue any day of the week, and connected
to that debate, there's an application of that debate ערב שבת, Erev
Shabbos, which happens to be יום טוב, Yom Tov, about using it
for a wick. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, ומדקבעי תרתי רב אדא בר
אהבה אליבא דרבי יהודה, Umedekabaei tartei Rav Adda bar Ahava aliba deRabbi
Yehuda, now since רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava explains
this debate according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about using a שבר
כלי, shever kli, שמע מינה כרבי יהודה סבירא ליה, shema mina keRabbi
Yehuda sevira lei, so we see that he holds like רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, or else he wouldn't have explained the debate that way.
Says the גמרא, Gemara, ומי אמר רב אדא בר אהבה הכי, Umi
amar Rav Adda bar Ahava hachi, did he really say that? ואמר
רב אדא בר אהבה, Ve'amar Rav Adda bar Ahava, top of דף
כט עמוד א, Daf Chaf-Tes Amud Aleph, נכרי שחקק קב בביקה, nochri
shechakak kav bevika, if a non-Jew makes a like
a—cuts out a type of a stump out of a log of
wood, ישראל מסיקה ביום טוב, Yisrael masika beYom Tov, so a jew
can use it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. I don't know exactly
why he's using this thing that maybe he's using the chips that
came out, but it doesn't matter. A log of wood was chopped
up and now you have some like little chops of things and
something new, it was carved into some stump, maybe to use as
a like as a false leg. And now, is it נולד? nolad?
Can you use it for יום טוב Yom Tov or not? Because
before it was a log of wood, now it's a new thing.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ואמאי נולד הוא Ve'amai, nolad hu? Why
is that true? It's נולד! nolad! And since he seems to rule
like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that like when a cloth becomes too
small, whatever, it changes its identity and you can't use it for
firewood, here too, this changed its identity. It changed it better presumably,
but you can't use it for firewood. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לדברי רבי אליעזר ורבי עקיבא קאמר, Lidivrei Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Akiva qamar,
you're right, וליה לא סבירא ליה. veleih lo sevira lei. And it's
right, he personally doesn't hold for רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. He holds
like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that we don't hold of this נולד
nolad idea. And if you could use this log of wood when
יום טוב Yom Tov began, you can also use it now that
it changed status and turned into a type of a, you know,
a type of a false leg. He doesn't hold that that's a—נולד
nolad is an issue for יום טוב. Yom Tov. But when he
was explaining the debate of the משנה, Mishnah, he explained it according
to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. They're holding
like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. He explained their debate, but that's not
his personal position. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
רבא אמר היינו טעמא דרבי אליעזר. Rava amar, hainu ta'ama deRabbi Eliezer.
Nah, you're making it too fancy, you want these debates connected. Nah,
it's a different debate. לפי שאין מדליקין בפתילה שאינה מחורכת, Lefi she'ein
madlikin bifsilah she'einah mechorachat, you can't use a wick that is not
singed. He feels that it does not draw the—hold the flame well
and it's like every other problem about using wicks for ערב שבת,
Erev Shabbos, that it will sputter out and it will—you'll fiddle with
it. ולא בסמרוטין שאינן מחורכין, Velo besamrutin she'einan mechorachin, and not with
rags that are not singed. So that's his problem. His problem is,
like it says, that you've twisted it, you haven't singed it. Singeing
it would change its identity from a cloth to a wick, make
it not be מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, but for him singeing does
another important thing. He happens to hold two positions that are unrelated.
The other position is, I don't want you to use wicks that
aren't singed because it won't hold the flame well, and that you
should singe it from before שבת. Shabbos. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
disagrees on both points: a twisted rag loses its identity for טומאה
טהרה, tumah taharah, and I have no problem with you using an
unsinged wick. So they're not related debates. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, אלא הא דתני רב יוסף ג' על ג' מצומצמות למאי הלכתא
Ela hadei tanya Rav Yosef, gimmel al gimmel metzumtzamos, lemai hilchesa? So
if that's true, how about this ברייתא Baraitha that רב יוסף Rav
Yosef says, exactly three by three? According to you, their debate isn't
limited to three by three. So the גמרא Gemara says, לענין טומאה.
le'inyan tumah. It's to tell you a
הלכה halakha about טומאה. tumah. דתנן ג' על ג' שאמרו חוץ מן
המלל דברי רבי שמעון וחכמים אומרים ג' על ג' מכוונות. Detnan: gimmel
al gimmel she'ameru, chutz min hamalal, divrei Rabbi Shimon. Vachachamim omrim: gimmel
al gimmel mechuvannos. When we say a piece of cloth has to
be three by three to be—to become טמא, tamei, does that include
the—like the fringes or not? Because if, you know, if you're going
to sew it on as a patch, then you're going to like
use the part that's probably not where the fringes are. So when
you say three by three, including the fringes or not including the
fringes? So that's a debate. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it—it doesn't
include—that it has to be three by three without including the—the fringes.
And the rabbis say three by three precisely, which means even including
the fringes. Okay, so therefore when we said exactly three by three,
it's interesting because you know, David Weiss Halivni,
Rabbi—Doctor Rabbi David Weiss Halivni, you know, he—explained sometimes that the סתם
stam of the גמרא Gemara has these teachings of אמוראים Amoraim or
these ברייתות Baraithas and they didn't sometimes always get what the original
context was. And here's like an
interesting... And exactly three by three, it starts burning it becomes מוקצה,
muktzah, you can't use it ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. According to another
approach, no, it's going on a משנה Mishna in כלים, Keilim, the
general הלכה halacha that the only thing that becomes טמא tamei is
a piece of cloth three by three, is it three by three
including the fringes or not including the fringes? Okay, and that's what
it's referring to. So there's a position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that says not including the fringes, חכמים Chachamim say exactly three by
three means it includes the fringes and it's not three by three
plus the fringes. Okay, so that's that. Now we though have introduced
a debate of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda and well we haven't said
the other opinion about using about נולד nolad on שבת Shabbos and
יום טוב Yom Tov and using things for firewood. Let's continue with
that. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, so
now רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, not רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda who was
before the תנא, tana, but רב יהודה אמר רב, Rav Yehuda Amar
Rav, the אמורא Amora says, מסיקין בכלים ואין מסיקין בשברי כלים דברי
רבי יהודה. masikin bekeilim ve'ein masikin beshivrei keilim divrei Rebbi Yehuda. Here's
going to sort of say what the debate of רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is. It's quite fascinating because it's
quoted as a ברייתא. braita. You know, normally here we know there's
a debate of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
by מוקצה, muktzah, but here the way he makes this statement, here's
what I think, I would say they would debate about the following
cases, right? Normally we would have expected it to say, you know,
you know רב יהודה Rav Yehuda would say even in this case
it's a problem, but he's the way he's saying it, it sounds
like he's quoting a ברייתא. braita. But here's what he's saying. מסיקין
בכלים ואין מסיקין בשברי כלים דברי רבי יהודה. masikin bekeilim ve'ein masikin
beshivrei keilim divrei Rebbi Yehuda. You can use vessels but not broken
vessels on יום טוב Yom Tov to for firewood, that's what רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says. ורבי שמעון מתיר, veRebbi Shimon matir, רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon says it's fine. It started שבת Shabbos as a vessel
even though it changed its status, it's not a נולד nolad problem
you can use it. מסיקין בתמרין, masikin betamarin, you can throw your
dates in the fire, אכלן אין מסיקין בגרעיניהן דברי רבי יהודה. achalun
ein masikin begarinieihen divrei Rebbi Yehuda. If you ate a date, you
can't throw the pits in the fire, דברי רבי יהודה, divrei Rebbi
Yehuda, that's what רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda would say. ורבי שמעון מתיר,
veRebbi Shimon matir, ורבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would say it's fine. מסיקין
באגוזין, masikin be'egozin, you can use nuts, throw the whole nut in
the fire, אכלן אין מסיקין בקליפתן דברי רבי יהודה. achalun ein masikin
bekelipatan divrei Rebbi Yehuda. If you ate the nut you can't throw
the shell in the fire, דברי רבי יהודה, divrei Rebbi Yehuda, that's
what רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says. ורבי שמעון מתיר, veRebbi Shimon matir,
ורבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would say it's fine. So it sounds like
it's all the same debate. Something that slightly changed its form on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, you can't use the non-usable part for firewood.
So the גמרא Gemara says וצריכא, utzricha, you need to tell me
all three. ואי אשמעינן קמייתא, ve'ee ashmeinan kamaisa, had you just told
me the first part about a broken vessel, בהא קאמר רבי יהודה
משום דמעיקרא כלי והשתא שבר כלי. beha ka'amar Rebbi Yehuda mishum d'me'ikara
kheli vehashta shever kheli. That I would say that's a real problem
of נולד, nolad, a real change of status. It started as a
vessel and now it's a broken vessel, completely different. והוה ליה נולד
ואסור, vehavei lei nolad v'asur, and it's נולד nolad and you can't
use it. אבל תמרין, aval tamarin, but dates, דמעיקרא גרעינין והשתא גרעינין,
d'me'ikara gar'inin vehashta gar'inin, there was always the pit. You just didn't
have access to it, but nothing really changed form. So there I
would say אימא שפיר דמי, eima shapir dami, maybe that's okay, it's
not a נולד nolad problem, the thing was always in the original
form. So therefore says even that case is no good. ואי אשמעינן
גרעינין, ve'ee ashmeinan gar'inin, if it just told me the pit, הוה
אמינא דמעיקרא מיכסן והשתא מיגליין. hava amina d'me'ikara michasya vehashta migalyei. Okay,
at least there it was covered and now it's exposed. So as
far as you're concerned, it's a new thing.
אבל קליפי אגוזין, aval klipi egozin, but the nuts of shells of
nuts, דמעיקרא מיגליין והשתא מיגליין, d'me'ikara migalyei vehashta migalyei, originally it was
exposed and now it's exposed. How did it change form? So אימא
שפיר דמי, eima shapir dami, that's not נולד. nolad. צריכא, tzricha, you
have to say that even that case is נולד nolad because even
that case originally it was serving the was connected to food and
was seen as part of foodstuff and now it's seen as
firewood. So its identity changes by not being connected to the food
even though it was always exposed and its form didn't change, its
identity has changed. And that's a type of a נולד nolad for
רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. So the גמרא Gemara says והא דרב, veha
d'Rav, and obviously so that's why you needed all three cases. And
to tell you that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon who allows, allows even
the more severe case of the broken vessel. והא דרב לאו בפירוש
אתמר אלא מכללא אתמר. veha d'Rav lav beferush itmar ela mikhlala itmar.
I already told you it was weird enough that this statement of
an אמורא רב Amora Rav is stated as if it's a משנה
Mishna or ברייתא braita of רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon what they debate, right? The language sounds like it's a straight
תנאי tannai source. And now we're saying he didn't even say it.
It was only inferred from the way he acted that that tells
us where רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon debate.
How where was it inferred? דרב אכל תמרי ושדא קשייתא לבוכיא. deRav
achal tamrei v'shada kashyasa l'vuchya.
רב Rav was ate dates and he threw the nuts the pit
into some into like an oven for firewood. This apparently was during
a weekday. אמר ליה רבי חייא, amar lei Rebbi Chiyya, so רבי
חייא Rebbi Chiyya said to him בר פחתי, bar pachti, which is
again a standard thing that רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya calls רב. Rav.
רש"י Rashi says sometimes it's an insult, sometimes רש"י Rashi says it's
a compliment. Here he says it's a compliment, it means like, you
know, a son of illustrious people. כנגדו ביום טוב אסור, kenegdo beYom
Tov asur, just be aware that if this was happening on יום
טוב Yom Tov you couldn't use the pit as firewood. So that
seems to rule like רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, obviously number one רבי
יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, there's a נולד nolad issue, and number two it
applies even to a pit of a date. So the גמרא Gemara
says alright, but קיבלה מיניה או לא קיבלה מיניה? kibla minei o
lo kibla minei? Did רב Rav if that's your whole basis, maybe
רב Rav didn't accept it, that was רבי חייא's Rebbi Chiyya position.
How do you know it was רב's Rav position? Maybe did he
accept it or not? So גמרא Gemara says תא שמע, ta shema,
come and hear, דכי אתא רב לבבל, dechi ata Rav leVavel, that
was when רב Rav was in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that's where
רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya was. When he left and he came to
בבל, Bavel, He ate dates and presumably this now is on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, you'll have to figure that out by context. He
ate dates ושדא קשייתא לחיותא v'shada kashaisa l'chiyusa and he threw the
the pit to the animals. So presumably saying it's not מוקצה, muktzah,
he went and he handled the pit afterwards and he gave it
to the animals. So מאי לאו, mai lav, so you see that
he holds it's not a problem. So מאי לאו בפרסיאתא, mai lav
b'parsyasa,
is it not that we're talking about פרסיאתא parsyasa which רש"י Rashi
says a type of a ripe date where the entire date is
removed from the pit and all you're left with is the raw
pit
itself? ולא קבלה, v'lo kibla, and we see he did not accept
the ruling, he held it was not a מוקצה muktzah problem. So
the גמרא Gemara says לא בארמיאתא, lo b'armyasa,
which רש"י Rashi says means an unripe date, so some of it
of the of the flesh is still adhering to the pit and
therefore it's not מוקצה muktzah because it still has some of the
of the flesh of the fruit on it. But if it was
just the pit itself, maybe he would hold it would be מוקצה.
muktzah. Okay. The ערוך Aruch says that this refers to actually a
type of a date where even the pit is somewhat edible. חזו
אגב אמיהו, chazu agav imaihu, since they are fit to eat via
their mother, meaning the mother ship, the main date itself. So according
to רש"י Rashi it means because there's still some flesh of the
date attached to it, and according to the ערוך Aruch it means
because they would be eaten together with it, it's still somewhat feasibly
edible.
Yes? He's feeding it to his animals, so is there really a
concern about benefiting from מוקצה? muktzah?
Yeah, well here we're seeing there's not. All these issues here were
about handling. So again, you know, but no, but the throwing to
the animals anyway was assuming it wasn't מוקצה muktzah and that's why
he was handling it. Okay, but the benefiting issue comes up with
the fire.
Do we really say that pits are מוקצה?
muktzah? Alright, so we haven't finished it. So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר ליה רב שמואל בר בר חנה לרב יוסף, amar leh Rav
Shmuel bar bar Chana l'Rav Yosef, לרבי יהודה דאמר מסיקין בכלים ואין
מסיקין בשברי כלים, l'Rabbi Yehuda d'amar masikin b'keilim v'ein masikin b'shivrei keilim,
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says that you can use
vessels but not broken vessels, כיון דאדליק בה פורתא הוו להו שברי
כלים, keivan d'adlik beh purta havu lehu shivrei keilim, so you made
your whole big deal about you know the cloth becoming a little
less than three by three. He says this is a problem anytime
you want to use anything and throw it in the fire. As
soon as it starts burning, it can no longer be used. Right?
So if you threw your I don't know, your wood jewelry box
in the fire, as soon as it started being lit, it it
becomes a שבר כלי, shever kli, you have to stop handling it.
וכי כמהפך באיסורא קא מהפך, v'chi kamahapech b'issura ka mahapech, and therefore
if you're turning it over in the fire, you're so again it's
not a problem about deriving benefit, it's a problem about handling. You're
handling מוקצה muktzah once it starts being lit. It's just like what
you tried to explain as the three by three cloth. So the
גמרא Gemara says אה, ah, here's the solution. דעבד כרב מתנא, d'avad
k'Rav Masna, you do like רב מתנא Rav Masna suggested. דאמר רב
מתנא אמר רב, d'amar Rav Masna amar Rav, עצים שנשרו מן הדקל
לתנור ביום טוב, eitzim shenashru min hadekel letanur b'Yom Tov, if wood
falls from the from the palm tree into the oven ביום טוב
b'Yom Tov on יום טוב, Yom Tov, so what do you do?
מרבה עצים מוכנים ומסיקן, marbe eitzim muchanim umasikan, you add prepared wood
and then you continue to burn them and you stir them and
it's not a problem. So basically you make רוב rov of it
non-מוקצה muktzah and then it's okay. Now what's the issue here? No,
maybe the issue here wasn't even handling, maybe the issue was deriving
benefit. We'll talk about that when we get to ביצה, Beitzah, that's
about a year away. Okay, but here the גמרא Gemara isn't concerned
about benefit, at least the גמרא Gemara here is concerned about handling.
Now why can you put a majority on it, why isn't that
a problem about אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה? ein mevatlin issur l'chatchila? Right,
you're taking איסור issur and you're making it בטל, batel, you're adding
kosher stuff in order to make it acceptable. So some ראשונים Rishonim
say actually maybe it is allowed, maybe that this is only דרבנן
d'rabbanan and not only that, the thing is burning away anyway, it's
not like even if you don't handle it it's going to burn,
it fell into the fire. So you're not really doing something to
allow you to benefit from it and so on and therefore you're
just allowing it to allow you to stir it, but it's not
really like you're מבטל mevatel and they give explanations about אין מבטלין
איסור לכתחילה. ein mevatlin issur l'chatchila. It could also be that part
of the issue here is not so much ביטול bitul as טלטול
מן הצד, tiltul min hatzad, right, when you're moving something on שבת
Shabbos or יום טוב Yom Tov מוקצה, muktzah, if you move it
incidentally it's okay. If you're reaching for the bread and to get
to the bread you're pushing something מוקצה muktzah out of the way
incidentally, you're not directly handling the מוקצה. muktzah. So maybe that's part
of the issue here as well. As long as the majority is
kosher wood, so then you are when you're you know then you
are now handling sort of primarily you're stirring the kosher wood and
the other stuff is more incidental. Anyway that is a question the
ראשונים Rishonim ask as well about מבטלין איסור. mevatlin issur. But that's
the answer. The answer is is that yes, it becomes a שבר
כלי shever kli and the only way you can continue to stir
the fire is if the majority is something else. Yes?
If you know that it's going to move is it still considered
accidental if it's before you make the move?
Yes, yes, as long as you're not sort of directly moving it
out of the way, your hand is like going here and it's
sort of moved by the side of your hand. Okay anyway a
lot of fun stuff to talk about, actually we'll get a lot
of מוקצה muktzah in מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbos as well. It's like
why you know after a while it starts feeling like every single
דף daf is either about בישול bishul or מוקצה. muktzah. Okay but
anyway, not yet. Or הוצאה, hotza'ah, those three. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
Okay. So now, so now we have two explanations. One explanation is
they're unripe. related debates, easiest explanation. One is, one debate is, can
you use unsinged wicks for שבת? Shabbos? And then the other debate
is, you know, when you twist something up, does it lose its
identity as a piece of cloth. Then there's a way to make
the debates connected. It's all about does it lose its identity? And
the problem is, a special case of יום טוב Yom Tov before
שבת Shabbos according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that when it starts
burning, therefore maybe it switches from a כלי Kli to a שבר
כלי Shever Kli if like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer it started as
a cloth to begin with. According to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that
it started as a wick, it doesn't change its identity and it's
not a problem. That's a way to make the debates connected. I
should by the way mention about this idea about a singed wick
that do we פסקן Pasken that way or not. So if you
take a look, right, because some people know that there's a מנהג
Minhag that the husbands get the candles set up for the wives
and they light the פתילות Ptilos and then they blow them out
and they singe them ahead of time. So if you look at
the end of תוספות, Tosafos, רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa Amar, תוספות
Tosafos says like this:
ונראה לי V'nireh Li says תוספות, Tosafos, the first narrow line of
תוספות, Tosafos, ונראה לי דבחינם נהגו אנשים להדליק הפתילה ולכבותה כדי שתהא
מואשת. V'nireh li d'bechinam nahagu anashim l'hadlik hapetilah u'lechabosah k'dei shetehei mu'evesh.
That it's for no purpose of a הלכה Halachic need that people,
men, maybe he means specifically men, I don't know, have the מנהג
Minhag to light it and to light it out and blow it
out before שבת. Shabbos. דהאי הלכה כרבי אליעזר, D'hai halacha k'Rabbi Eliezer,
we don't rule like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, דשמותי הוא, D'shamusai hu,
he was either in חרם Cherem or he was from the house
of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and we see later on that it's
not necessary. So anyway it's not really necessary, that's only רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer's position. Nevertheless, say the ראשונים, Rishonim, it's still a nice
מנהג. Minhag. Okay, anyway, does make it easier to light when you
come around to lighting it. Now the גמרא Gemara continues and says
the following: רב המנונא אמר, Rav Hamnuna Amar, רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna
says הכא בפחות משלושה על שלושה עסקינן. Hacha b'pachus m'shlosha al shlosha
askinan. Here we're talking not exactly three by three but less than
three by three but it's a different three by three. Until now
we were talking about less than three by three fingers. Now at
the whenever you're doing three by three you gotta really hope that
it's spelled out and doesn't say ג על ג. Gimel al Gimel.
Here it's שלושה על שלושה, Shlosha al Shlosha, three by three טפחים.
Tefachim. Okay, so three by three טפחים, Tefachim, I mean even three
by three fingers is a problem. Why does this matter? Because if
you remember yesterday or the day before we learned that three by
three טפחים Tefachim is a more serious בגד. Beged. One נפקא מינה
Nafka mina is other materials might be considered to be a בגד,
Beged, you know, clothing, not in small sizes but three by three
טפחים Tefachim yes. Here's another way in which it's different. How easily
something loses its status as a בגד. Beged. If it starts exactly
at three by three, it's holding on by a thread, excuse the
pun. Anyway, so there it's easier to lose its status if it
starts by three by three fingers. If it starts by three by
three טפחים, Tefachim, maybe it's harder to lose its status. So let's
take a look. Here we're talking about less than three by three
טפחים, Tefachim, ומקולי מטלוניות שנו כאן. U'm'kulei matlaniyos shanu kan. And this
is about the sort of the leniencies or not leniencies but sort
of like the the light type of work, the insignificant type of
usages that you put a rag to. דאזיל רבי אליעזר לטעמיה ורבי
עקיבא לטעמיה. D'azil Rabbi Eliezer l'taamei v'Rabbi Akiva l'taamei. And now I
can make debate based on another debate of רבי אליעזר ורבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Akiva. So before we were trying to make the
שבת Shabbos issue connected to the טומאה Tumah issue. Now he's got
an approach to make this debate of רבי אליעזר ורבי עקיבא Rabbi
Eliezer v'Rabbi Akiva connected to another debate. דתנן, D'tnan, we taught in
the משנה Mishna in כלים, Keilim, פחות משלושה על שלושה שהתקינו לפקוק
בו את המרחץ ולנער בו את הקדירה וללקנח בו את הריחיים. Pachus
m'shlosha al shlosha she'hitkino l'fkok bo es hamerchatz u'lenayer bo es hakedirah
u'lekanayach bo es harechayim. So this is what we mean קולי מטלוניות,
Kulei matlaniyos, you're using something that was a cloth and was normally
for a garment and now we're using it for some, you know,
unpleasant שמאטע, Shmatte, exactly, a שמאטע Shmatte purpose. So you take something
that is less than three by three, and what is it at,
and what do you want to do? You now are going to
use it to be a stopper for your bathhouse, to you know
to plug up the not the the whatever the pipe, or לנער
בו את הקדירה L'nayer bo es hakedirah as a, no, not a
shender, it's a potholder, as a potholder, so that you can turn
over the pot, or לקנח בו את הריחיים L'kanayach bo es harechayim
or just as a שמאטע Shmatte to clean the to the mill.
בין מן המוכן בין שאינו מן המוכן טמא. Bein min hamuchan bein
she'eino min hamuchan tamei. Whether it is something that is normally would
have been designated for use of a of a cloth, or whether
something that maybe you were in the process of throwing out, it's
still is טמא. Tamei. It's still is, even though it's less than
three by three, and even though you have assigned it this sort
of, you know, this menial work, it's still is a cloth, it's
more than three by three fingers even though it's less than three
by three טפחים, Tefachim, and therefore it can still become טמא. Tamei.
דברי רבי אליעזר. Divrei Rabbi Eliezer. That's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says.
רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says בין
מן המוכן בין שלא מן המוכן טהור. Bein min hamuchan bein she'lo
min hamuchan tahor. Whether it is something set aside for use as
a cloth meaning as a piece of clothing, whether it was something
that was you were throwing out, we'll see in a minute what
that means. Anyway, once you have designated it for this type of
use, for this שמאטע Shmatte use, it stops being cloth and it
is טהור, Tahor, even though it is more than three by three
fingers but because it's less than three by three טפחים. Tefachim. So
again it's easier to lose its status once it's less than three
by three טפחים, Tefachim, and therefore it becomes טהור. Tahor. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva splits his vote. אומר מן המוכן טמא, Omer min hamuchan
tamei, if it was something that was going to be used for
clothing then now that you've designated it for that he did for
a שמאטע, shmata, still טמא. tamei. שלא מן המוכן, shelo min hamuchan,
if it wasn't set aside for clothing, טהור, tahor, it's going to
be טהור. tahor. Okay, so now this is the debate of רבי
עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva middle position, but nevertheless, that's what's going on in
our משנה. mishna. Again, has nothing to do with the שבת shabbos
issue. שבת shabbos issue is: do you need to singe your wicks?
Here it's a different issue. You have taken a piece of cloth
that's less than three by three טפחים, tefachim, more than three by
three fingers. So normally it would be טמא. tamei. But you have
designated it for שמאטע shmata use, for wick use. So רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says, 'I don't care what you designated it for. It
still is, it can become טמא. tamei. It's more than three by
three fingers.' And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, 'At least in some
of the cases and maybe we'll see in the end all the
cases,' he says 'once you've designated it for the שמאטע shmata use
and it's less than three by three טפחים, tefachim, it stops being
cloth and it's טהור.' tahor. ואמר עולא ve'amar ula and עולא ula
said, דתימא de'teima רבה בר בר חנה rabba bar bar chana אמר
רבי יוחנן, amar rabbi yochanan, הכל מודים hakol modim זרקו באשפה zarko
be'ashpah דברי הכל divrei hakol טהור. tahor. Everybody agrees that if you
took this cloth and you literally threw it in the garbage, that
that make, and it's less than three by three טפחים, tefachim, that
makes it טהור. tahor. Then it stops being a cloth. הניחו בקופסא,
henicho be'kupsa, if you put it in a box where you keep
all of your like, you know, your sewing
materials, דברי הכל divrei hakol טמא. tamei. Everybody says it's טמא, tamei,
you're still going to use it for some type of a cloth.
לא נחלקו אלא שתלאו במגוד lo necheleku ela she'tala'o be'magod או שהניחו
אחורי הדלת. o she'henicho achorei hadelet. We're talking only that you hung
it up on some type of a frame or you left it
behind your, you know, on the floor behind your door. It wasn't
fully thrown out, it wasn't fully in your knitting box, your sewing
box. So it's an ambiguous state and therefore it's the debate of
how easily it loses its identity as a cloth. רבי, Rabbi, and
all you did by the way, you didn't start using it, right?
Remember, if you like, once you singed it, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
agrees it becomes a wick. All it says is you designated it.
You said, 'Oh, you know what? That thing it's on the floor,
ach, I'll just use it for my bath, or I'll just use
it for my שמאטע.' shmata. But you haven't used it yet. Does
it change its status? Okay, and it's in this sort of ambiguous
state right now in this ambiguous place, and you've designated it for
this other use. רבי אליעזר סבר מדלא זרקו באשפה, rabbi eliezer savar
mide'lo zarko be'ashpah, look, you didn't throw it in the garbage, דעתיה
עילויה, da'atei alavei, you're still going to, you still, even though it's
behind your door, whatever, who knows, you'll change your mind, you'll use
it for clothing. ומאי קרי ליה שלא מן המוכן? u'mai karei lei
shelo min hamuchan? Why does he call it it's not מן המוכן?
min hamuchan? דלגבי קופסא לאו מוכן הוא. de'lgabei kupsa lav muchan hu.
Even though he says it's still considered clothing, he calls it שלא
מן המוכן, shelo min hamuchan, it's not because it's not fully designated
like clothing, it's not like it's in your sewing box. But he
still holds as long as it hasn't, you haven't yet used it,
you've just designated, even if on the floor, who knows, you have,
it's still possible you'll use it for clothing, it could still be
טמא. tamei. And it still hasn't changed its identity. רבי יהושע סבר
מדלא הניחו בקופסא, rabbi yehoshua savar mide'lo henicho be'kupsa, בטולי בטליה. bitulei
batlei. If since you didn't put it in your clothing box, in
your sewing box, eh, you've, you've negated it, you're no longer using
it as cloth. And therefore, what, and therefore it loses its identity.
ומאי קרי ליה מוכן? u'mai karei lei muchan? So why does he
say even something מוכן muchan loses its identity? It's not מוכן. muchan.
מוכן muchan would be טמא. tamei. This is not מוכן, muchan, he's
claiming that this is טהור. tahor. No, he says, דלגבי אשפה מוכן
הוא. de'lgabei ashpah muchan hu. It's more designated for clothing than if
it had been in the garbage. But his point is, even though
this is somewhat designated for clothing, because it's not fully designated, he
says it can become טהור tahor once you set it aside for
שמאטע. shmata. As opposed to רבי אליעזר, rabbi eliezer, רבי אליעזר rabbi
eliezer says even though it's somewhat not designated, like it's behind the
door, since it's not fully non-designated, like fully thrown in the garbage,
it will always remain in its status and remain able to become
טמא. tamei. רבי עקיבא, rabbi akiva, רבי עקיבא rabbi akiva splits his
vote. בתלאו במגוד סבר כרבי אליעזר, betala'o be'magod savar k'rabbi eliezer, בהניחו
אחורי הדלת סבר לה כרבי יהושע. behinicho achorei hadelet savar lei k'rabbi
yehoshua. If you put it on a frame, he thought like רבי
אליעזר, rabbi eliezer, it's close enough to still being in the clothing
category and it can become טמא. tamei. If it's behind your door
then and you plan to use it for a שמאטע, shmata, then
it can become, then it's טהור. tahor. And now the גמרא gemara
says, so that would have him as a split vote. והדר ביה
רבי עקיבא לגבי דרבי יהושע. ve'hadar bei rabbi akiva legabei de'rabbi yehoshua.
רבי עקיבא rabbi akiva actually reversed himself and really fully sided with
רבי יהושע rabbi yehoshua and says it's always טהור. tahor. ממי? mi'mai?
And how do you know it? So אמר רבא מדקתני, amar rava
mide'ktani, if you assume that's what's going on in our משנה, mishna,
that our משנה mishna proves that רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda doesn't make
this distinction. Because he said פתילת הבגד, psilat habeged, the, a twisted
piece of cloth. מאי איריא דתנא פתילת הבגד? mai irya de'tana psilat
habeged? Why did it say a twisted cloth? ליתני פתילה של בגד.
lisnei psila shel beged. It should have said a twisted sort of
like piece of cloth. If it called the thing a twisted cloth
clothing בגד, beged, it calls the thing itself a בגד. beged. So
מאי פתילת הבגד? mai psilat habeged? דעדיין בגד הוא. de'adayan beged hu.
Even if you would normally say this is still a piece of
cloth, even if normally it would have been on the frame and
it would have been something that you would have been inclined to
think still has its identity as cloth, nevertheless once you've designated it
and twisted it, it loses its identity. Presumably not if it's in
your clothing box, then it's clearly different but... Anything that's ambiguous, once
you've designated it for this type of שמאטע shmatta or wick use,
it loses its identity. So it is by the way interesting that
the גמרא Gemara makes the debate about like what state the thing
is in. We still have five minutes. We're going further. The גמרא
Gemara makes the debate
what type of status the thing is in, whereas you could have
said that no, the debate is even if it's in a clear
context behind the door, in your sewing box, whatever the context is,
maybe the debate is until you actually have applied it to the
new use, right? It doesn't change its identity, like the משנה, Mishna,
until you actually have singed it. But the גמרא Gemara tries to
say that actually maybe they do agree in certain contexts where the
context makes it clear enough what its identity is, even though it
physically hasn't changed its status. So what have we explained now is
the debate? Whether it's טהור tahor or טמא, tamei, we basically have
the possibility about just whether twisting something that is, you know, changes
its status or not. And then the גמרא Gemara sort of said,
you know what, that actually maybe ties in a little bit to
this other debate about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer about something less than three by three טפחים tefachim and designated
for a שמאטע shmatta type of a status, how quickly does it
lose its old identity or not? So that seems to be the
טומאה tumah debate. And how about the issue about using it for
a wick? Either it's an independent issue of do you have to
pre-singe your wicks? Or it's a linked issue about יום טוב Yom
Tov before שבת, Shabbat, and once it goes from a כלי kli
to a שבר כלי shever kli becomes a problem. But if it
would always have been a wick, it was, it already started יום
טוב Yom Tov not having been a wick, then it would not
be not having been clothing but having been a wick, then it's
not changing its status, it's not נולד. nolad. Let's take a look
now at the next משנה. Mishna. I want to see if we
can get a whole דף daf ahead. לא יקוב אדם שפופרת של
ביצה וימלאנה שמן ויתננה על פי הנר בשביל שתהא מנטפת. Lo yikov
adam shfoferet shel beitzah viyimalena shemen viyitnena al pi haner bishvil shetehei
menatefet. Oh, we only have three minutes. Okay, anyway, but still. Don't
make a, take a, what do you call it, a eggshell or
something that looks like an eggshell and fill it with oil and
put it by the lamp in order that it should drip. Okay,
so you basically have some type of a container of oil suspended
above the lamp with a little hole in the bottom and it's
slowly dripping into the oil in the lamp and replenishing the oil.
ואפילו
היא של חרס, veafilu hi shel cheres, even if this isn't a
literal eggshell, even if it's made out of pottery, it's a problem.
רבי יהודה מתיר, Rabbi Yehuda matir, Rabbi Yehuda says it's okay. אבל
אם חיברה היוצר מתחילה, aval im chibrah hayotzer mitchilah, if it was
originally fashioned as one unit with the, with the, you know, with
the lamp, it was a fancy lamp that came with this whole
drip thing in it, מפני שהוא כלי אחד, mipnei shehu kli echad,
then it's permitted because it's one vessel. We don't even know what
the problem is. We'll see in the גמרא Gemara what the problem
is. לא ימלא אדם קערה של שמן ויתננה בצד הנר ויתן ראש
הפתילה בתוכה בשביל שתהא שואבת, Lo yimaleh adam kearah shel shemen viyitnena
btzad haner viyiten rosh haptilah betochah bishvil shetehei shoevet, and similarly don't
have a separate bowl filled with oil next to your lamp and
run the wick of your lamp out of your lamp and into
the bowl. So it's sort of, it's like a second tank. It's
a refill tank. So now it's drawing oil both from the lamp
oil and from the bowl oil. רבי יהודה מתיר, Rabbi Yehuda matir,
and Rabbi Yehuda allows it. Now what's the problem? The גמרא Gemara
is going to explain that the problem is because it's not directly
the oil of the lamp, you'll forget that it's replenishing the oil,
you'll dip your bread in it and you'll indirectly cause the lamp
to go out before the time, you'll remove oil that's designated for
the lamp and that'll be כיבוי kibuy or גרם כיבוי gram kibuy
extinguishing the lamp before the amount that it would have burned.
Even with the wick in your...
what? Yeah, but it's still it's a separate bowl, you won't see
the wick. That's the concern. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. Let's just read a little bit in the גמרא. Gemara. וצריכא,
utzricha, you need to tell me both cases about the eggshell and
about the separate bowl. אי אשמעינן שפופרת ei ashmeinan shfoferet של ביצה
shel beitzah בהא קאמרי רבנן, beha kaamri rabanan,
that's where the rabbis say it's not a problem דכיון דלא מאיסה
dikivan delo meisa because it's not disgusting, it's an eggshell, אתי לאסתפוקי
מינה, ati lestapuki minah,
you'll take from it, you'll dip your bread into it. אבל של
חרס aval shel cheres דמאיסה, demeisa, it's disgusting, אימא מודי ליה לרבי
יהודה, eima modei lei le-Rabbi Yehuda,
maybe they'll agree with Rabbi Yehuda, nobody's going to dip your bread
into oil held in a thing of pottery. ואי אשמעינן של חרס
vei ashmeinan shel cheres בהא קאמר רבי יהודה, beha kaamar Rabbi Yehuda,
that's where Rabbi Yehuda said it's okay because you won't dip, because
it's disgusting. אבל בהא aval beha אימא מודה להו לרבנן, eima modeh
lehu lerabanan, he'd agree to the rabbis that you'll forget and dip
your bread into it. ואי אשמעינן הנך תרתי, vei ashmeinan hanach tarti,
had it just said those two variations of the eggshell, בהני קאמר
רבי
יהודה, behani kaamar Rabbi Yehuda, that's where Rabbi Yehuda says it's okay,
you won't forget, משום דלא מיפסק mishum delo mifsek because
there's nothing that separates it from the lamp, it's directly over the
lamp and you'll... and you won't
forget. אבל קערה aval kearah דמיפסקה, demifseka, if it's in a different
sort of vertical plane than the lamp, it's separated from the lamp,
so אימא מודה להו לרבנן, eima modeh lehu lerabanan, maybe he'll agree
to the rabbis that you'll forget that this is filling up the
lamp and you'll come to dip your bread into it.
ואי אשמעינן בהא, vei ashmeinan beha, and if we just told me
the last case, בהא קאמרי רבנן, beha kaamri rabanan, fine, that's the
case the rabbis are concerned about. אבל בהני תרתי, aval behani tarti,
maybe with the egg that's directly over, אימא מודו ליה לרבי יהודה,
eima modu lei le-Rabbi Yehuda, maybe they'd agree to Rabbi Yehuda. צריכא,
tzricha, so you need to tell me. They debate the whole full
range of cases where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is concerned that it'll
lead to you drawing from the, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is not
concerned and he allows it. The rabbis are concerned it'll lead to
you dipping your bread in it and will lead to כיבוי. kibui.
So we will pick up with this tomorrow.